<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An address for submissive, peaceable, and loving living together under the present government to the people of the commonwealth of England, however by some called royalists, Presbyterians, independents, or fifth-monarchy-men / by Tho. Moore, senior.</title>
            <author>Moore, Thomas, Senior.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2589A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10798011</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10798011</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45953</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45953)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1406:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An address for submissive, peaceable, and loving living together under the present government to the people of the commonwealth of England, however by some called royalists, Presbyterians, independents, or fifth-monarchy-men / by Tho. Moore, senior.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Thomas, Senior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Cottrel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45953:1"/>
            <p>AN ADDRESS FOR Submiſſive, peaceable and loving living together, Under the Preſent Government, To the People of the COMMONWEALTH OF ENGLAND, However by ſome called, ROYALISTS, PRESBYTERIANS, INDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PENDENTS, or FIFTH-MONARCHY MEN.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Moore,</hi> Senior.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hearken unto me, that God may hearken unto you.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As much as is poſsible have peace with all men.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>James Cottrel,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45953:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45953:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To all Chriſtian Readers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Chriſtians,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas many of the People of this Commonwealth, have testified both their thankefulneſs for, and ſubmiſsion to the preſent Government, by making their Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Recognitions to his Highneſs the
<hi>PROTECTOR,</hi> in one of which Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, my Name alſo is: Be not you offended, That I in teſtmony of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God for his Mercies in, and of deſire of Love among our ſelves, and peaceable living under the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:45953:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do make my Addreſs to you; firſt giving my Ground, and then making my Requeſt to you, with endeavour of anſwering what I conceive in any of us might hinder the Acceptance. For any weakneſſes of mine in this attempt, let Charity prevail ſo far to paſs hy, as not to be prejudiced therewith; but that which the Scripture calleth for, and I according to the Scripture requeſt, accept my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in deſiring of you: I being for peace, I pray let none of you be for war, among our ſelves; but each endeavouring peace, that we may ſhare in that Promiſe, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Peace-makers:</hi> and ſo fear God, and love one another, and live in peace among our ſelves; and the God of peace be with us: which is the prayer of the leaſt and unworthieſt of all God's Mercies and Servants,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Moore.</signed> Wittleſey,
<date>April 7. 1656.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45953:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45953:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45953:4"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rom. 13.1,2.</bibl>
                  <p>Let every ſoul be ſubject unto the higher Powers, for there is no Power, but of God; the Powers that be, are ordained of God: whoſoever thereſore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ankinde being fallen under ſin and death, and ſo liable to have the curſe, &amp; death by ſin deſerved, executed on them all:
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23. &amp; 5.12,18. Heb. 10.6,9. Gal.
3.13. Rom 14.9. 1 Cor. 6.19,20. 2 Cor. 5.14,15.</note> Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God interpoſing, hath for Mankind, ſuffered that deſerved death and curſe, and ſo redeemed Mankind from the curſe of the Law: and by his Death, Reſurrection, and Sacrifice offered to God. hath bought all Men of God, and is become their rightful Lord, inlightning and extending means to them, that, as they are not their own, but his; ſo they might live to him that is their Saviour and Lord.</p>
            <p>And God hath given all Power and Authority to him, and all over into his diſpoſe, and made him Lord of all, and doth by him uphold and order all things;
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.27 &amp; 28.18. Act. 2.36. &amp; 10.36. Col. 1.17. Heb. 1.3. Pſa. 75.3.</note> ſo that it is indeed by him, (whoſe Sacrifice was vertuous from his firſt undertaking, though more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted ſince acted) that the Earth is upheld, and the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45953:5"/>thereof, and the Governments among them therein:
<note place="margin">Prov. 8.15,16.</note> 
               <hi>By him Kings raign, and Princes decree juſtice; by him Princes rule, and Nobles; all the Judges of the earth.</hi> And all that God doth in ordering the Sons of Men, he doth it in and through his Son Chriſt, and according to the Covenant and Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Father and the Son, in the Sons firſt undertaking for Mankinde;
<note place="margin">Joh. 5.19,20,22,23.</note> and ſo and in that manner, God ruleth for ever by his Power and his Kingdom ruleth over all;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.7. &amp; 103.19. Dan. 4.25,35,37. Pſa. 57.6,7.</note> yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even in the Kingdom of Men, and gives it to whomſoever he will, and none can ſtay his hand, and ſay unto him,
<hi>What doſt thou? So that pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion cometh neither from the Eaſt, Weſt, or South: but God is Judge himſelf, he putteth down one, and ſetteth up another.</hi> So that it is evident, That there is no power but of God. The words alſo here give us to underſtand it of the Dominion, Rule, Authority, and Power of Magiſtrates, called here, <hi>The higher Powers,</hi> as appointed and ordered by God that is the higheſt Power, his Son, the Great King, that is higher than the higheſt of them;
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.8. Rev. 11.15,17.</note> but doth not yet take his great Power into his own hands perſonally to raign with his Saints; but as he hath given the earth to the children of men, ſo he giveth the Power of governing into the hands of ſome men, whom he calleth <hi>Mighty Ones,</hi> or <hi>Gods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> to judge among the Sons of men for God, &amp; to give account to him, when Chriſt comes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to judge:
<note place="margin">Pſa. 115.16 Pſa.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo that the Powers that in any Age or Nation are in being for Magiſtracy in a Commonwealth, they are of God; and whether for mercy or chaſtiſement, they are ordered by God in the ſame love, and to the gracious end, in which he gave Chriſt, &amp; made him Lord. And here to underſtand Powers for Magiſtracy in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, is evident in the Text &amp; Verſes following, &amp; alſo in the Apoſtles charge to <hi>Titus</hi> to teach the ſame Doctrine to Believers,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>To put them in minde to be ſubject to Principalities, to obey Magiſtrates.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> alſo teacheth the ſame, putting it as one chief part of an honeſt Converſation,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>14,15,17.</note> 
               <hi>To ſubmit our ſelves to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Ordinance of man,</hi> (that is, humane Ordinance or Creature, <hi>viz.</hi> Princes, Magiſtrates, Governours, which God hath made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally by Men, whether by Birth, Election or Conqueſt) <hi>for the Lords ſake; whether it be to the King, as ſupream; or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent</hi> (or ſet in Office)
<hi>by him,</hi> &amp;c. and ſhewing this to be the will of God,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> he joyns <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45953:5"/>theſe two together, <hi>Fear God, and honour the King;</hi> which term by the whole context appears to be the chief Governour, and thoſe ſet in Office of Government by him: for, as Hiſtory ſaith, <hi>The chief Governours in thoſe dayes were called Emperours:</hi> but whether Emperour, King, Prince, Protector, Judge; all are included in ſaying King or chief Governour, Principalities Powers, Magiſtrates: and that theſe Powers are the Governours of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, is cleer, in ſaying, <hi>The Powers that are,</hi> or <hi>are in being;</hi> and ſo the like at any time in being: for as for ſuch kinde of Powers, wielded with ſuch a Sword in ſpiritual and Church-Aſtairs, though before Chriſt offered up the acceptable Sacrifice, there was ſomething like in the
<hi>Aaronical</hi> Prieſthood (though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then the Kings were in the Throne above them) yet now Chriſt is come, the High Prieſt after the Order of
<hi>Melchizedec,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining himſelf the High Prieſt for ever, having in that no Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, the Prieſthood being changed, there is of neceſſity a change of that Law.
<note place="margin">Heb. 7.11. Mat. 20.25 28. Luk. 22 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>27 Mat. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>12. 2 Cor. 1.24. 1 Pet. 5.2,3. Rev. 13.1,2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>8. &amp;
11.1,2.</note> And Chriſt hath forbidden it to all Church-Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, in forbidding his Diſciples and Apoſtles the having and uſing any ſuch Dominion, Lordſhip and Titles among them, or allowing and giving it unto others. And the Apoſtles according to the command of Chriſt have diſclaimed all ſuch Lordly power, and charged all Church-Officers to do the ſame; nor could any Church. Officers have and exerciſe ſuch a Power, till the Dragon gave his Seat, Power, and Authority to the Beaſt: of which Power is not here meant, and ſo I have no occaſion in this buſineſs to treat of it; but of the Powers, or Governours of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, of which the Apoſtle directly ſpeaketh, and ſo every of them, that in any Age or Nation are in being; that which is in being, poſſeſt of the Power, it is ordered of God, he in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs ſeeth, and ſo ordereth it, as that which for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing his ends, is fitted for us: and his will and Ordinance is, That we acknowledge his Wiſdom, Soveraignty and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſubmitting to live peaceably and obedently under the ſame. And he that reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God: whence every Soul, even of Believers, ought to be ſubject to the Power in being; and ſo the Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts and Elders, were; and the Church with all her Officers, are to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Principalities and Powers that are in being, and ſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45953:6"/>As for fleſhly Objections, under pretence of Spirit, by ſome Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, that which is ſaid of the loweſt in Power, being much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be heeded in reſpect of them that are higher in Power; we have anſwer given to them in Scripture.</p>
            <p>If any ſay,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.18. Col. 3.22. 1 Tim. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>I am a Believer and made free by Chriſt, a Son of God; and he that ſits in the Chair of Government, is an unbeliever, and ſo in bondage to Satan; it is not meet for him to govern me, or for me to be ſubject to him:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is anſwered,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.13. Job 4.17.</note> The Liberty given us, is not for an occaſion to the fleſh, and <hi>ſhall mortal man be more pure than his Maker?</hi> it is God that in his Wiſdom and for his Ends hath ſet him in place of Government, and thee in place of Subjection: it is therefore right, for all his works are right; and thou that hateſt right, art of all others, moſt unfit to govern.
<note place="margin">Job 34.12.13-17.19-23.42<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>32.</note> Therefore if thou counteſt God, that ſet him in place of Government, wiſe, righteous, holy and good; count him God hath ſet as Governour above thee, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy all that eſteem, honour, reverence and ſubmiſſion that by Gods command is due to the Governour.</p>
            <p>But if thou have not this to object, and the folly in thy deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful heart move thee to a contrary reply; ſaying, <hi>I am a Believer, and he in place of Government is a Believer alſo; we are both free in Chriſt, and there is no difference of bond or free in Chriſt; we partake of the ſame Grace, and priviledges, and hope; we have one Father, one elder Brother, and we are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; why ſhould one Brother rule over another? He taketh too much upon him:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou art anſwered,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>3,4. Eph. 6.5. Col. 3.22 Philem.
12.13,14,15,16.</note> He ruleth not over thy Faith and Conſcience, but over thy Body and outward affairs; and to help thy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, a diſtinction is afforded thee, between <hi>In the Lord,</hi> and <hi>In the Fleſh;</hi> and <hi>after the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>according to the Fleſh:</hi> that we may not confound <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the natural Man and the ſpiritual Man, the Commonwealth and Chriſt, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Grace, in one: and ſo if thoſe Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> that be our Governours, be alſo Believers; if the Governours of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth be Members of the Church; if he that ſits as Man in place of Government, be alſo in the Faith, and ſo a Brother; then Believers are to eſteem, love, ſubmit and obey ſo much the more cheerfully, and the more readily, becauſe they are faithful
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45953:6"/>and beloved: ſo that if Governours, poſſeſt of the Power of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, be Heathen or Infidels, yet the Power of Magiſtracy they are poſſeſt of is of God, and ordered by God. If the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates be Believers, and ſo Chriſtians and Brethren, their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanity annibilates their Magiſtracy, no more then Grace deſtroyeth Nature, or the Church the Commonwealth; but helps for the good and profitable exerciſe thereof; and ſo without any queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on asking for Conſcience ſake, about our ſubmiſſion to Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers, and obeying Magiſtrates What Religion do they moſt affect? how are they qualified or diſpoſed? how came they to be poſſeſt of the Power? by Birth and Inheritance, or by Election of the people, or by Conqueſt? If God in his providence hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that Power, and poſſeſt ſuch of that Power, we are to look at the ordering hand of God; and knowing him to be good, to believe him to do good: and ſo, whether he hath ordered them for mercy or chaſtiſement, yet to ſubmit to, and not to reſiſt the Powers; but in all their commands, that we may do, though to our own damage, obey them. In things before commanded by God, obey them more readily and cheerfully: if any of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands be to deny or diſ-obey God, yet reſiſt not the Power, but refuſe doing the Command, and ſubmit to ſuffer the puniſhment they will inflict; and this with patience before the Lord, that comes ſo to try us: and ſo if we will not leſiſt, but pleaſe God, it behoves us all, every man, and ſpecially Believers, ſo to be ſubject to the Higher Powers, as is fully and plainly declared and commanded, in places alledged, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1-7. <hi>Tit.</hi>
3.1,2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13,14-17. And many Evidences. Demonſtrations, Reaſons and Motives might be given, to move and preſs as hereunto; but that Explication would be tedious: as to ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Jer. 27.5,6,7,8.</note> The undoubted Soveraignty, Right and Authority of the Lord, the earth being his, and they that dwell in it; he having made all, and being the upholder of all, having alſo bought all men to be in his diſpoſe, ſo as he may put them under what Governours he pleaſe: and thoſe that will not ſerve thoſe under whoſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he puts them wo will be unto them.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Deut. 2.5,9 19-23. Joſh 12. Ezek.
29.19.</note> As he hath Right, Authority, and Wiſdom, Power and Godneſs, to uſe it; ſo he doth rule for ever by his Power, and hath according to his will given the ſeveral parts of the earth, firſt to <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45953:7"/>one, then to another to poſſeſs, and govern;
<note place="margin">Dan. 2.37. 2 Chron. 36.33.</note> and given Kingdoms and Commonwealths, according to his will, as in Scripture we may read at large.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.4,5,6. &amp; 19.11,13. Deut. 28 48. Judg. 17 6. &amp; 18.1. &amp; 21.25. Heb 1.14. Jer. 3.15 Pro. 29.2 &amp;
11.10,11.</note> When he is ſo provoked by a people, that in diſpleaſure he will chaſtiſe them though for gracious ends; then he will give chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren or fools to be their Princes or Rulers, or their enemies to rule over them; or, which is the heavieſt of all, deprive them of having any King or Ruler, when every one will do his own will, and one man devour another: and when his face ſhines upon a people, to make the Righteous rejoyce, he gives them Shepherds according to his heart, and ſets the Righteous in Authority.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 135.6. Eccleſ. 3.14 Job 23.13,14 &amp;
34.29.</note> What he will do, he doth in this buſineſs, and none can withſtand him, ſo as to add to, or take from this buſineſs he doth; but whether for mercy or chaſtiſement, ſuch as he puts in power ſhall be in power for the time appointed by him.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 82.1-7 &amp; 33.10,11 Rom. 13.3,4. Prov.
19.21. &amp; 26.10 &amp; 29.26. &amp; 16.10.</note> As he doth all things rightly, ſo when he putteth men in power, he giveth them a charge, and they ſhall give account to him; and however they intend or proceed, yet they muſt give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to him; and he ordereth all their Judgements in the iſſue not to fulfil any of their vain counſels, but his counſel and ends; and though many ſeek the Rulers favour, yet every mans Judgement ſhall be as the Lord ordereth it, who oft puts a Divine Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the Rulers Lips, that the Judgement of the Lord is pronounced; and that ſurely to be ſubmitted to, as from the Lord.</p>
            <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Act. 4.26-28. Pſa. 2.1-6. Gen. 45.4,5. &amp;
50.20. 2 Sam. 29.5,8. &amp; 30.1-19. Dan. 3.13-30. Rev. 7.14,15.</note> In thoſe things wherein men deal and judge moſt unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and the innocent undergo the greateſt injury, yet God hath his ordering hand therein, to bring light out of darkneſs, and makes it in the iſſue, to come forth to the greateſt good of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers, and of others alſo that love the Lord, which will ſupport all that take all out of the hands of God in the believing acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his Government, as we may ſee, not onely in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Chriſt, but of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and others. And to move us to this ſubmiſſion.</p>
            <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.27 Mat. 17.25-27.</note> We have beſides the command of God, the example of our Lord and Saviour; though Lord of all, yet as he was Man, and Miniſter of the Goſpel here on Earth, he behaved himſelf as a Servant, even among his Diſciples; and both payed Tribute him<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45953:7"/>ſelf to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and counſelled others ſo to do;
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21 Joh. 18.11. &amp; 19.11.</note> and taking all his ſufferings out of his Father's hands, he reſiſted not the ſentence of <hi>Pilate;</hi> but acknowledged, That he could have had no power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, if it had not been given him from above. Therefore whoever will acknowledge the Soveraignty, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Power of God, in his ruling by his Power, and diſpoſing Power and Government to the Sons of Men, muſt in that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, even for the Lord's ſake, and the glory of his Name, be ſubject to ſuch Government, as he ordereth to be over us. And this is to do it in ſingleneſs of heart, as to the Lord: and he that doth not on this Ground ſubmit to the Powers that are in being, will finde occcaſions of diſcontent, to keep him from a ſingle-hearted Submiſſion, if the Powers he deſireth were granted to him: ſo that even then he will be a Murmurer and male-content. Therefore let us on this ground ſubmit.</p>
            <p>And if any enquire, <hi>What is that obedience and ſubmiſſion we are on this ground to render to Magiſtrates:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, Even the ſame which the Scripture on this ground re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth us; which appeareth to be,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17. 1 Tim. 6.1. Pſa. 119.68. Ecc.
10.20. Exo. 22.28</note> That we do honour them, in reverence and eſtimate of the Power ordered to them, as that which is right, and beſt for us in that frame we are found in; and ſo beware we curſe them not in our hearts, nor revile them with our tongue, or ſo endeavour to render the Magiſtracy infamous.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1,2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>5.</note> That we reſiſt not the Power by riſing up or rebelling againſt it; but if its injunctions be for ſuch things, as in conſcience to God we cannot do, then ſubmit to endure their puniſhment, if they will inflict it.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Prov. 24.21,22.</note> That we joyn not with ſuch, as are not content with the Powers God ordereth; and if afflicted, will not with patience wait till God ordereth it to be more merciful; but of themſelves will be ſeeking and endeavouring to change: meddle not with ſuch, have no confederacy with them.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.6,7.</note> That we yield unto them that Tribute, that Cuſtome, and that Fear that is due unto them.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> That we be ready to every good Work required by them, for the Preſervation, Safety, and Commodity of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:45953:8"/>6.
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.2,3.</note> That we ſhew all meekneſs and patience towards a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> though many of the Aſſeſſors and Collectors, for thoſe works ſhould behave themſelves churliſhly and fooliſhly.</p>
            <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.17,18,19. &amp; 13.3,4,8,9,10. 1 Pet.
2.12,13.</note> That we defraud or injure no man, nor revenge our own cauſe; but in love endeavour as much as is poſſible to live peaceably with all men, and ſo innocently in the Nation and Commonwealth in that Government we are under.</p>
            <p n="8">8.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.4.</note> That if the Spirit of the Ruler riſe againſt any one, That he do not raſhly fly, but humbly ſubmit: if the Spirit of Satan raiſe Perſecution againſt the Truth, if the way be opened, one may fly to eſcape, and ſpread the Truth farther; or in weakneſs, to avoid the ſnare of denial: but if it be onely the Spirit of the Ruler againſt a Man, yielding will pacifie great offences.</p>
            <p n="9">9.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1,2,3,4. Jer. 29.7. Pſal.
37.1-7.</note> That we pray to God for his teaching, governing and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving thoſe in Authority, and making them inſtruments of good to us and the Commonwealth, and ſo pray for the peace and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the Commonwealth and Nation we live in: and thus not fretting our ſelves, or being envious againſt evil doers, but doing good, we may dwell in the Land, and be fed.</p>
            <p>And thus it becomes us to ſubmit to, and obey Magiſtrates, even as they are, and becauſe they are Magiſtrates, whatever they be, ſo long as God continues them in their Power over us.</p>
            <p>But if theſe Magiſtrates have other Ornaments put on them by God, (beſides their ſimple Magiſtracy) in which they have ſome reſemblances of our Lord and Saviour Chriſt upon them, then there is more abundant goodneſs extended by God to us in them, and more obligations ſtill to thankfulneſs for them, and cheerful ſubmiſſion, and ready obedience to them; as to ſay,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Deut. 18.15 18. Jer. 30.21.</note> If the chief Governour be one of our ſelves a Country-man, a Kinſman, of our own Country and Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Deut. 1.2, 37. &amp; 2.</note> If he have undergone hardſhip in ſufferings and ſervices with us and for us.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.11.</note> If God hath honoured him to be an inſtrument to us of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from any hard ſlavery and bondage, and of enjoyment of ſafety in peace and liberty.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Nehem. 2.10.</note> If being ſet in Power, his bent and Buſineſs be, to protect and ſeek the welfare and peace of the people in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,<pb facs="tcp:45953:8"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45953:9"/> 
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45953:9"/>and eſpecially of ſuch as fear God, that they may live quiet and peaceable lives, in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
            <p n="5">5.
<note place="margin">Pſa. 101.6,7</note> If to this end he endeavour to purge out wicked Officers, and ſet up Men fearing God, for Under-Judges and Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p n="6">6.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.</note> If he love the Church of God, and be himſelf even one of them, rejoycing with them in fellowſhip in the Ordinances of God, ſeeking the peace and proſperity of the Church: if ſo, then in theſe things he reſembles, not onely <hi>Moſes, Joſhua, David, Nehemiah,</hi> but in ſome meaſure the Lord himſelf: and if for the Lord's ſake we ſhould ſubmit to, and obey Magiſtrates, though evil men; how much more, if God give us ſuch a Governour, are we to be thankful for, and ſubmit to, obey and live cheerfully and quietly under ſuch a Government?</p>
            <p>Therefore having ſo good ground for my requeſt, I pray you. men, fathers, and brethren of this Nation and Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> take it well that I make this addreſs to you; beſeeching you, that now God hath been ſo gracious to us, and dealt ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully with us, that none of us be like thoſe wicked Adverſaries that grieved that one was come to ſeek the welfare of God's peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<note place="margin">Nehem. 2.10. Gen. 45.24.</note> nor let us fall out one with another, but be at peace, and ſo with thankfulneſs to God ſubmit to, and live quietly under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment God hath ſo extraordinarily given us, and ſealed his minde in his manner of putting us under it; in which we have ſuch Teſtimonies of his mercies, and ſtreams of his goodneſs, that knowing his minde for our ſubmiſſion, I need uſe no other motives to perſwade: onely I ſhall aſſay to remove ſome thoughts, that hinder the ready ſubmiſſion of ſome; and for that, is the reſt of my requeſt in my addreſs to you all.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You dear Friends, that plead your Obligation and Affection to the Governour and Government that fore-was in the King and his Succeſſors, I commend your then-Affection and Faithfulneſs in its ſeaſon, in and according to that Obligation; in which, ſo long as with God's allowance I might. I ſtood one with you: but God hath by a power even iſſuing from that power, ſignally with his own hand changed that, and ſet another Power up that is in being, and the very Succeſſor of what went before. I need ſay no more: a Child is to honour his Father; but if his Father be dead, and his Mother married to another man, the ſame Law bindes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45953:10"/>him to honour him that is now his Father. I might give many ſuch inſtances, and fortifie them with Scripture alſo:
<note place="margin">Dan. 1, &amp; 2 &amp; 4, &amp; 5.11-13. &amp; 6. &amp;c. Ezek. 17.12-21. Jer. 38.16-20. &amp; 29.</note> but I ſhall onely pray you confider the example of that holy Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in holy writ; he was faithful to <hi>Nehuchad-nezzar;</hi> yea, and to his Son
<hi>Belſhazzar</hi> alſo, (and what became of the unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Prince and Princes, that ſubmitted not to be faithful in that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, when God had put them under it, nor would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded thereto, is known: but
<hi>Daniel</hi> was faithful) yet when God by providence put that Government and Governour out of being, and ſet up another, even the <hi>Medes</hi> and
<hi>Perſians,</hi> who won that Power by conqueſt; <hi>Daniel</hi> ſubmitted to and followed the Lord; and was as faithful to <hi>Darius,</hi> as ever before to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchad-nezzar;</hi> he knowing that the moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will; when God had ſet up another Power, he was ſubject unto that:
<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4. Pro. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>And this is written for our inſtruction, That we may walk in the way of good men.</hi> What troubles befel ſuch as would not ſubmit to, and live under the Government God hath ſet over them, we may read at large in Scripture.
<note place="margin">Jer. 29. &amp; 41, &amp; 42, &amp; 43, &amp;
44.</note> And how God hath reſiſted and teſtified againſt ſuch as have enterprized Rebellion to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment he by providence puts us under, even the dim-ſighted may ſee. Let therefore the Apoſtolical charge take place with us, and let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers that are in being, knowing they are ordered of God. If you cannot fully digeſt this counſel, yet till you can, you may digeſt <hi>Gamaliel</hi>'s counſel, to ceaſe oppoſing;
<note place="margin">Act. 5.38,39.</note> 
               <hi>For if this counſel, or this work be of men, it will come to nought; but if it be of God, ye cannot overthrow it, leſt happily ye be found even to fight againſt God.</hi> And I hope, in conſidering what God hath done, and what the Scripture ſaith, you will ſee that the ſetting up this Power is of God, and ſo digeſt the Apoſtles counſel alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You my dear Country-men, that from the Authority of the King and Parliament, and ſo from the Authority of Parliament, iſſuing from and confirmed by the King, did from and in obedience to that Power, lift up your hands and proteſt before God, to be faithful to that Power: and alſo, when that Power had in its a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation, ſomething purged and new moulded it ſelf; ſo, as the Houſe of Lords was down, and the King departed, even then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45953:10"/>proteſted to be faithful to that ſtill remaining Power of the Government of the Commonwealth of
<hi>England,</hi> as it then ſtood, without King or Houſe of Lords; and on diſſolution of that Power, many made their Addreſſes to the Chief in Military Power, for calling a free Parliament; and by vertue of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, voted for Members; and ſo by Act and Hand, avouched his Authority. Did not you, as I do, all this to God, in obedience and ſubmiſſion to him, acknowledging him the Orderer of all Powers; and ſo ſubmitting to the Power he hath poſſeſt of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? if you did it not on this ground, you were weakly carried and byaſſed with ſome baſe ends, which far be it from me to judge: and if you did it on this ground, then have you not onely ſeemed, but really involved your ſelves in the Obligation of Faithfulneſs to the Protector and Government that is in being; and ſo your own heart will ſay as much to you as I can, <hi>That every Soul of us be ſubject to the higher Powers that are in being.</hi> Nor are a few grievances any toleration to us for unfaithfulneſs: but ſurely we have none, but what the neceſſity in Providences diſpoſing hand puts on us; nor are we loaden with any burthen, or hindred of any advantage, nor drawn to any ſervice, which in our own former Engagements we did not oblige our ſelves unto. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hope you are well pleaſed with, and will be obedient to the Government God hath put us under: and I pray you let us lovingly and peaceably ſo walk together in our obedience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now you dear Fathers and Brethren, who for the love of Jeſus Chriſt, and in deſire to pleaſe God, and approve your hearts to him in your Faith, Worſhip and Converſation, and did in times paſt lovingly agree together in Union of Affection and Profeſſion for this deſign, and could bear ſome differences then in other Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, where this deſign was found to be agreed in; and then the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and trouble complained of, was, the impoſition of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rites, and Doctrines, and Traditions of men, the lordly Rule of BBs, the evil proceedings of their Courts, and want of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to worſhip God according to our Conſcience: for attempting and preſſing after which, ſome were impriſoned, and ſome loſt blood and life, ſome were ſilenced, many cited, and many drawn to their Courts, and ſome excommunicated, and ſome occaſioned to flie into other Countries: by reaſon of all which, they that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45953:11"/>feared the Lord went under the terms of Puritans, Preciſians, Factioniſts, Schiſmaticks, and diſobedient to Authority; and ſo made the odium and ſcorn of the common people; derided, abaſed,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then glad in ſecret to meet, for Faſting, Prayers, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. In thoſe dayes we loved one another; and profeſſed, might we enjoy Liberty of Conſcience, for enjoyment of, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in the Goſpel, bread and cheeſe, mean fare and mean accommodations for the outward man ſhould content us. This was a time of ſadneſs; but now God hath tried us, and we are found not upright in what we profeſſed, as our many diſcontents and complaints do teſtifie; even now when God hath freed us from thoſe burthens and complaints we then groaned under, and given us a Protector and Government, under which we enjoy more Liberty of Conſcience and fellowſhip in the Goſpel, than we could then have thought of, if we did not fall cut among our ſelves; and becauſe our particular luſts are not ſatisfied, ready to fault and murmur againſt Governour and Government alſo, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the Wilderneſs againſt
<hi>Moſes,</hi> after their great deliverance; but their murmurings were againſt the Lord, as it's to be feared ours alſo will be found to be: an ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital of ſo great mercy, once ſo highly prized, and earneſtly prayed for; and now received, ſo lightly eſteemed: it brings to my minde the ſaying of a godly Miniſter in thoſe times, who loved me, and I him; and having ſome communion together, though our Habitations were far diſtant on occaſion of ſome ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in which we fully agreed not; <hi>I thank God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that ſuch differences as this breeds no diſ-union nor diſ-affection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us; I deſire it might be ſo with all that fear the Lord: but we have a common enemy,</hi> (meaning the BBs.) <hi>that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes us all; and we may thank God for it, for by that means we are kept at peace with, and love to one another: and if that common enemy be once removed, then ſhall we fall out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our ſelves.</hi> He that ſaid this, is now with God; I that heard it, am yet living on this earth, to ſee his words verified. I am ſorry we make no better uſe of God's mercy, and return ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to him for ſo great good done us: I pray God give us to be humbled for it; and now in love and thankfulneſs to him, and love to one another, to lay aſide vain-glory, envy, bitterneſs, wrath,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45953:11"/>anger, evil ſpeaking, and help us to be kinde one to another, and tender hearted; not every one ſeeking his own things, but each the good of other; and then may we enjoy the benefit of the mercy given us, and ſo be thankful for and live comfortably under the Government God hath ſo graciouſly ſet over us; for which my Addreſs is to you, which one might think needleſs for ſuch as we; and if it be needful for ſome, as it appeareth it is, yet it is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult for me to make it rightly, becauſe of the diverſity of mindes among us; I pray therefore bear with me, and accept it, while I endeavour it as well as I can: and ſo I make my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You reverend Fathers and Brethren, whoſe minde and bent is ſet for a National, Provincial, and Claſſical Presbytery, for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Government of Church-affairs; and to have the Power of the Magiſtrate to confirm and ſtabliſh the ſame; and ſo to give ſuch Power to you, that by the Power of the Magiſtrate, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to you, you may ſet up and carry an end the ſame; and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content if the Magiſtrate afford you not this Power. Surely, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der among Brethren, and in Church-Aſſemblies and Affairs, is needful, deſireable, profitable and beautiful; and even that in having Officers alſo: yet that it is ſo needful, deſireable, profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and beautiful for outward Order, to be alwayes, in all Ages, or in all Nations, or in all Congregations, or in every or all the parts of any one Country or Province the ſame, I nowhere finde in Scripture;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.26-40. &amp; 11.2,3 4.</note> but this I finde, a true Church, and for ſpiritual gifts, highly enriched and commended, and Order required; and yet no outward Officers mentioned; yea, probable, becauſe of their diviſions, not betruſted to chuſe their Officers, till the Apoſtle came and ſet ſuch things in order;
<note place="margin">Act. 14.21-23.</note> yet were they true Churches in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> as there were divers in other places, that were true Churches for ſome time before they had any ſuch outward Officers. And I alſo read, how in the ſame time and Age, in another place, that in the Church there was Biſhops, (or Elders) and Deacons, (or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) to help in Miniſtration;
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.1. Act. 6.3-6.</note> and eſpecially, for the relief of the poor; and this a Church as much approved, as any I know: and yet I finde in <hi>Crete</hi> and <hi>Epheſus,</hi> divers Churches that had Biſhops, (or Elders) and Deacons;
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5-xi.</note>and alſo a Biſhop or Elder appointed to overſee all the Churches in that Province, with their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45953:12"/>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.3-5. &amp; 3, &amp; 5.</note> Biſhops &amp; Deacons, to admoniſh them both for right Doctrine and Manners, and to be chief in helping them both for ordaining and confirming both of Elders and Deacons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Crete,</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> in <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.28,29,30. Eph. 4.7-13 1 Tim. 3. 2 Tim.
2. &amp; 3, &amp; 4.1-5. 1 Tim. 6.11,14.</note> To ſay <hi>Timothy</hi> and
<hi>Titus</hi> did this as they were Evangeliſts, is but a ſaying without proof: for as the names of Apoſtles. Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors, Teachers, were not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to Eccleſiaſtically called Church-Officers; but to all thoſe ſo gifted by Chriſt, and other Officers called Biſhops &amp; Deacons, or Elders and Deacons: ſo the work of an Evangeliſt is ſet out plainly and fully to be in teaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this the command to be kept till the appearing of our Lord Jeſus: and though men ſo gifted be fitteſt for ſuch overſight alſo, yet no neceſſity, yea, or poſſibility, to have alwayes the like outward order in Church-Officers and Government, though Churches differing in ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form may be alike true and good both in Doctrine and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and that among them all was done in Faith and Love by the Word, and ſuch ſpiritual power and weapons as the Word af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded them, without craving power of the Magiſtrates of the Commonwealths, or deſire of any part of their Sword, to carry an end, and manage their buſineſs with. So it was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the firſt Chriſtian Churches, in the beſt times: ſo that, reverend Fathers and Brethren, you may perceive, I do not fault, but juſtifie rather the Order deſired by you, though the terms of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of it be obſcure; yea, I could as willingly be under the ſame, ſo I might enjoy the ſoundneſs of Faith, and Liberty of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual fellowſhip with Brethren of another outward Order, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to have been under the BBs with Freedom from their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Injunctions, and to enjoy the foreſaid Liberty; for the order and power of this and that is one and the ſame, if rightly uſed, onely called by different Titles: but this is that which is faulty, and occaſions faultineſs, The deſire of the Magiſtrates Power, to impower you to eſtabliſh and carry an end this Order; for which you have neither Word nor Example of Chriſt, or any his Apoſtles, Prophets or Evangeliſts, nor any thing like, but the by-gone Law of the
<hi>Aaronical</hi> Prieſthood. Oh, my Fathers and Brethren, did you ſo mourn for the Tyranny of this Power in the BBs hands, and would you have it in yours? was their lording Power over their Brethrens Faith and Conſcience ſo evil in your<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45953:12"/>eyes, and will the ſame be good in your hands, when onely the Title of Lord, and ſome groſs outward Superſtitions are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way? was Liberty of Conſcience for all Fearers of the Lord ſo good, and much to be deſired when that power was in their hands? and is the ſame now a curſed Liberty and toleration for any but thoſe that ſubmit to have that Power in your hands, and come under your Order, when many tender Conſciences of your godly Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren can no more digeſt your Order, than they could the former? I hope the moſt of you by this time are better perſwaded, than to be ſoliciting the Governour to give Power into your hands, to rule over your Brethren. It's enough, we are protected, and you have Liberty for going on, and winning in, all that by Word and good Converſation, you prevail with to joyn in that Order. I hope this contents you, ſo that you will not murmur at, but be thankful for the Government; and preſs for no farther Power, than the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection it ſo lovingly affords you: as for thoſe whoſe Spirits are ſtill carried to enjoy that Power in their hands, do they not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by either juſtifie the Power they pretended againſt, and ſo teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it was not conſcience of ſinfulneſs in a lordly Power in Miniſtery of the Church, nor the lordly Power they ſought to pull down; but the taking away thoſe Perſons and Titles, and exalting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the ſame Power? or elſe their mindes are altered, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to have that builded and eſtabliſhed, of which once they complained and ſought to pull it down. Surely, ſuch may thank God that the Governour affords them not their deſires; for did he, they would hurt both him, and themſelves, and others alſo, as much as their fore-Fathers did: but I hope there remains not many thus minded. Therefore my requeſt is, That we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider well the mercies God hath given us in the Government he hath ſet over us, and what an Inſtrument of Mercy the Governour is made to us. Surely, we are eaſed of that, which (if our hearts were right) was our greateſt grief and complaint. And there is Liberty for that deſired Order, as far as by Scripture, Truth, Teaching, and holy Converſation, and warrantize from God, may be reached unto; yea, more then when we faſted and prayed, we did expect in anſwer of our Prayer. Let us not grutch our Brethren to enjoy the ſame mercy with our ſelves, that prayed, and have their Prayers anſwered with us; but in thankfulneſs to him<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45953:13"/>that anſwereth our Prayers, praiſe God, and thank him for our Government, and pray for our Governour, and live together in peace and love under his Government, not biting one another, leſt we be conſumed of one another; and if we be per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect, and of one minde to glorifie God, and live in peace, the God of peace will be with us, and bleſs our Protector and us alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And you, beloved Fathers and Brethren, whom ſome ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly call <hi>Independents,</hi> I hope you have as much as your Souls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Protector, as Protector, and in the Government in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of your perſonal and ſocial Concernments in that Liberty and protection that is afforded you: ſeeing, whatever by the Word and your holy Converſation, according to the light and knowledge given you, and bleſſing of ſucceſs afforded you, you have even outward Liberty to congregate, and receive into your Congregations, and to order for Offices and Exerciſe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Conſcience and underſtanding of the Word; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection herein alſo. I know you deſire not worldly promotion, nor any power of the Magiſtrate, to Lord it over your Brethren, that in ſome things diſſent from you, and accord not in all things in your Order in congregating: and ſo you do readily, that which my Addreſs is for. And ſo my Requeſt to you is, That we may in ſingleneſs of heart to God, and love to one another, perſevere in Thankfulneſs and Prayers for the Inſtruments of our Mercy, and not by diſcontented Thoughts ſuggeſted by any, be waved; but live peaceably with acknowledgement of the Mercy given us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government over us: and that we may ſo do, let us nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judge nor deſpiſe our Brethren, fearing the Lord, though in ſome things they diſſent from us;
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.1,18.</note> walking according to the light they have received, and not according to all that light we conceive our ſelves to have received; nor murmur at, or preſs the removal of ſome things that agree not with our Judgements about a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſtery in the Nation, and the maintenance thereof. You know, that new Wine put in old Veſſels, will break the Veſſel, and both Wine and Veſſel will be marred: and every thing is beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its time; and ſome things of that Nature can yet hardly be done with Righteouſneſs: and beſides, as Chriſt is a Saviour, ſo his followers principal aim in their agitations, is ſaving; and the ſudden doing of ſome things of that Nature, would produce raging,<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45953:13"/>hardening, deſtroying rather than ſaving them, till by degree they be brought to a fitter capacity, And if we remember God's gracious order in dealing with us, to bring us to that we now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, and wait with patience for others, to win them with loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs, and minde God's hand, who knows what is fitteſt for us, and when; and pray to our heavenly Father for bleſſing, guidance and protecting of our Protector, and his Council<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he that hath heard and anſwered us thus far, will certainly, ſo far as is good for us, hear and anſwer us farther; onely let us not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value, but improve the opportunities already given us: and ſo in thankfulneſs for, walk ſubmiſſively to, and peaceably un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government God hath given us. I need ſay no more to you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But for you beloved Fathers and Brethren, that believingly look for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that once abaſed himſelf, and died for us, and hath procured us ſo much good by his Croſs; and by vertue thereof, extends ſo much mercy daily to us, to come again perſonally in glory, and to take to him his great Power, &amp; ſit upon the Throne of
<hi>David</hi> his Father, and raign; and all his Saints to come with him, and raign with him; and ſo all the Kingdome under the whole Heavens, to be given to the Saints of the moſt Hight It is marvel to me, that any of you ſhould be diſcontent at the Government, under which you enjoy ſo many mercies; that you cannot with thankfulneſs live quietly under it, and wait with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for that day. If in my Addreſs to you for this, I come
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in touching ſome goodly appearing thoughts; yet he that loveth, there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him: and I hope, Love will ſo lead me, that I ſhall offer no juſt occaſion for love to be provoked or ſtumble at.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you ſay, <hi>Your deſire is, that Chriſt may raign in his Saints; and your grief and offence taken, is, becauſe it is not ſo:</hi> then I pray let us begin at home, and we ſhall finde the greateſt cauſe of grief for this, to be within our ſelves; and in this deſire, I am perſwaded not onely our Protector, but all Saints in this Commonwealth are one with us; for Chriſt raigning in his Saints, in this Day of his Grace and Patience, is not his raigning with and by his Saints, in making all of them the outward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Governours of the men of this World; but raigning and<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45953:14"/>living in his Saints by his Word and Spirit, ſubduing every Thought to the Obedience of Chriſt;
<note place="margin">Cal. 2.20. 2 Cor. 10.3,4. &amp; 4.13. 2 Tim.
1.7. 1 Cor. 9.19-27. 1 Joh. 5.4,5. Rev. 12 11. &amp; 3.10. Act. 9.4,5. Col.
1.24. 2 Tim. 2.12.</note> and them to accept the Croſs of Chriſt, and Conformity to him in it; and ſo by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Faith, Love, Power, and a ſound Minde, he dwells in them, and they live to him; and yet are in this World for his ſake, as he was, ſubject to humane Powers, and Servants to all for their good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and though they overcome the World, yet the Victory is by Faith, proceeding to more ſpiritual goodneſs; and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Weapons, reaching to worldly Power and Honour over men: but by the Blood of the Lamb, and the Word of their Teſtimony, not loving their lives unto the death; ſo, as while he raigns in them, they keep the Word of his Patience, and are Sufferers for him, and with him, and he with them; who ſhall after raign with him, when he raigns: and this I hope you all believe; and this alſo, That Chriſt his raigning in his Saints, hath been from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ever ſince he had a Church on Earth;
<note place="margin">Pſa. 68.18,19. 1 Cor. 2 14. 1 Joh. 3.1. 1 Cor.
1.4,5,6. Col. 1.12,13. Rom. 14.1-17. &amp; 15.1,2,3. Rev. 11.15-18. Col. 3.4. 2 Theſ. 1.7-10. 1 Theſ. 1.10.</note> and more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly and manifeſtly, ſince he compleated his Sacrifice, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced our Nature in himſelf to Heaven, and ſent forth ſuch plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful gifts of the Holy Ghoſt; and ſo doth in this Day, though the men of the World cannot perceive it; and our eye-ſight ſo weak, that a little duſt of ſome difference ſo blindeth us, that we can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcern it in our Brethren diſſenting from us, (though in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) ſo as to give thanks as the Apoſtle did for the
<hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Coloſſians;</hi> but need rather that admonition given to the <hi>Romans;</hi> but the Saints raigning with Chriſt, and his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal raigning with and by them, as it is yet to come, ſo it comes at once, and they begin together: when he comes, and takes to him his great Power, and raigns over the Kingdoms of the World; then, and not till then, ſhall his Saints ſo raign with him: he that believeth on him, makes not haſte, nor deſires to raign before his Maſter; but waits for that, till the Lord comes from Heaven: and when by providence he putteth any Saint into a place of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power and Government; yet in that alſo, they will be found Sufferers with their Maſter, and Strangers in this World, as Saints; and though Protectors of their Brethren the Saints in their outward Peace, yet Rulers of them as men alſo in their outward affairs, and not able to carry all as they would in and by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Officers and Under-Governours in this World: wo is us, if<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45953:14"/>they ſhould ſuffer any thing by us, for whom queſtionleſs they ſuffer much;
<note place="margin">Pſa. 75.2 &amp; 72.4. &amp; 39.12. 2 Sam.
23.5. Heb. 4.7-11. &amp; 11.8-16. 1 Theſ. 1.9,10.</note> ſo, that we cannot look to have all without fault here, we muſt wait for that till our Lord and Maſter himſelf doth come: even thus it was with <hi>David.</hi> And ſo the time of the Saints reſt, and raigning with Chriſt over the men of the World, is not yet. It is better for us to have Chriſt raigning in us now, and to look for our raigning with him, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and our Fathers did for the Inheritance and Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If any of you ſay, <hi>We agree in this, onely we would have Chriſt to be ſet on his Throne:</hi> I anſwer, To deſire and haſte to that Day, All Saints that believe ſuch a Day, as in which Chriſt ſhall ſit on his Throne, do aſſuredly joyn with you: but before that Day, to deſire or attempt to ſet Chriſt on his Throne, none that rightly underſtand and well ponder the buſineſs, dare joyn with you in deſire or eſſay. I beſeech you conſider with me but theſe things, which I hope you believe, as I do.</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.21. &amp; 4.2. Pſa. 103.19. &amp; 66.7. Heb. 8.1. 1 Pet. 3.22. Joh. 5.17,19,20. Prov. 8.15,16. 1 Pet. 2.2,3-9. Pſa.
110.1. Act. 2.33,37. &amp; 3.19,20.</note> That the Throne of Chriſt he is now upon, is the Throne of the Father; and he, and he onely as man, and no man but he, is already ſet down with his Father on his Throne, nowhere called
<hi>The Throne of David;</hi> but, <hi>The Father's Throne, The Throne of God,</hi> that is ſet in Heaven; where he, even the Man Chriſt, now is ſet on the right Hand of God, all Power and Authority given unto him; ſo, as God doth all by Jeſus Chriſt: and he doth all both from God, and as God: and ſo he ruleth by his Power for ever, and his Kingdom ruleth over all; and by ſuch Magiſtrates as he pleaſeth, he ruleth the Sons of men; and by his gracious Word and Spirit he gathereth a people to himſelf, and ruleth in their hearts and ſocieties.</p>
            <p>And thus is Chriſt by his Father ſet with his Father upon his Throne; and there to continue, till he make his Enemies his Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool, which is the time of the reſtauration of all things; and then none ſhall fetch him down, but the Lord ſhall ſend him <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſurely this Government of his, while he ſits with his Father on his Throne, it becomes us all to ſubmit to, both in his providential or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Governments among the Sons of men, and his ſpiritual Regiment by the Goſpel in the Church; and all this without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, or appointing him his way; yea, it is beſt even for the<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45953:15"/>Kings and Judges of the Earth, to kifs and ſubmit to him, and not to oppoſe him whom God hath made Lord of all; not at the requeſt of any, to aſſay to pull him from his Father's Throne, to ſet him on another; if we ſhould defire ſuch a thing of our PROTECTOR, it is a great mercy to be denied. But yet.</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly, Conſider farther concerning ſetting Chriſt on his Throne;</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Micah 4.8. Luke 1.32.</note> What manner of Throne it is, and whoſe it hath been; and the Scripture will tell us, it is
<hi>Davidical,</hi> and ſo in the promiſe of it, called, <hi>The firſt Dominion;</hi> and expreſly, <hi>The Throne of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Father David:</hi> and that was neither above in the Heavens, not in the Hearts and Conſciences of Men, in which Chriſt was before, and is above <hi>David;</hi> but the Throne on which
<hi>David</hi> ſate, much exalted, ſhall he ſit on and raign.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">Jer. 3.17. Iſa. 24.23. &amp; 33.20,21 &amp;
62.7. Pſa. 132.13-17 &amp; 122.3-5.</note> Where the firſt, chief and continuing place of this Throne on which he ſhall fit; ſhall be; and the Scripture tells us, It is <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Sion,</hi> the City where
<hi>David</hi> dwelt, in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> where <hi>Abraham</hi> ſojourned. This <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Canaan</hi> made new and beautified, ſhall be the place of his Throne, and the praiſe of the whole Earth.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.7,16 &amp; 1.13,14.</note> What is to be done by him before he ſit upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and raign, and all his raign with him, and this the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture declares to be, To continue his ſpiritual gifts in and unto the Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s, to perfect them for the work of the Miniſtery, till the laſt man be brought in that ſhall be called by this Miniſtration of the Goſpel-Call;
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.30 Acts 1.11. &amp; 3.20,21. Rev. 22.20 Phil. 3.20,21. 1 Theſ. 1.10. &amp; 4.14,15,16,17. 1 Cor. 25.52,53,54.</note> that we All (not <hi>ſome</hi> onely, but <hi>all</hi>) meet together in the Unity of the Faith, and of the Acknowledgement of the Son of God, unto a perfect Man, unto the meaſure of the Age of the fulneſs of Chriſt, meet to be poſſeſſed of the purchaſed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: and then, that the Lord Jeſus do perſonally and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſcend from Heaven, in the ſame body in which he died, and roſe, and appeared to his Diſciples, and aſcended up to Heaven, where he yet ſitteth on the right Hand of God, and maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us; for whoſe ſo coming the Saints long and waits and then in this his deſcending from Heaven, that he do in a moment raiſe the Saints that ſleep, and change the ſurviving, that together
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45953:15"/>at once they may ſee the Lord, and meet him in the Air; ſo to be ever with him;
<note place="margin">Zach. 14.4,5-9. Iſa. 13 9,10-1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſa. 149.5,9. 1 Cor. 15 24,25,2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and ſo being met, then that he come, together with all his Saints, and overturn all the Powers and Governments of this World; and ſo put down all Rule, Authority, and Power, that the <hi>Davidical</hi> Government may rule all, till all be given up to the Father; and ſo God be All in all. True it is, when he comes to do this, whoever of the Governours of this World in any of the Nations be found a Saint, ſhall in the ſame moment be changed, and meet him, and come with him to this work; and for the reſt, ſuch as at the firſt, on the appearing and coming of Chriſt with all his Saints, ſubmit to ſerve him and his people, ſhall have their lives prolonged, though their Dominion be taken away.
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.12. Iſa. 60.12. Mal. 4.2,3. 2 Pet. 3.7. Jude 14,15. 2 Theſ. 1.8,9. Iſa. 9.4,5,6. &amp; 11.4 Pſal. 72.4. Act.
3.19,20. Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19,20,21,22. Iſa.
65.12,13,14-17. Rev. 21.</note> But all that then refuſe and rebel, ſhall be deſtroyed and burnt up both root and branch: This being the Day of Perdition and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to ungodly men; and this not like other battels, in which ſome die on both ſides; but with burning and fuel of fire, by the Breath of his Lips: and this done, then will he reſtore all things, free the Creation from its bondage, and make the Heaven and Earth new, for a righteous people to dwell in: and this done, and not before, he will ſit upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and then ſet his Saints on Thrones to raign with him. And ſo the Seripture directs us to look for this day.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Joh. 18.36. Pſa. 2.6-9. Ezek. 33.23. Act.
3.19,20. Pſa. 132.11. Dan. 4.44. &amp; 7.13,14,27. 2 Tim. 4.8. Rev. 2.26. &amp; 3.22.</note> Who is to ſend him forth, and ſet him upon his Throne. Surely, he is not to receive his Kingdom, or be ſet on his Throne after a worldly manner, or by any of this worldly Powers, or Weapons, that his Souldiers ſhould ſo need to ſight for him; nor ſhall the Saints ſet him upon his Throne; yea, the moſt High God, he, and he onely it is, that at the ſeaſon ſends forth this Son of Man, and giveth him the Throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and ſetteth him thereon; and of him onely he receiveth it, and ſo ſitteth thereon; and being ſet on his Throne, he it is that giveth the Kingdom to his Saints, and ſetteth them on Thrones. This Honour is his.</p>
            <p>True it is, before his perſonal appearing to do all this, many Earth-quakes and ſhakings of worldly Powers will be; and the Ten Horns hating the Whore, and making her deſolate and naked, eating her fleſh, and burning her with fire;
<note place="margin">Mat. 24. Rev. 17.16.</note> the Horns enriching themſelves with their ſpoils; in which battel, the Saints as Men,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45953:16"/>and as called by Authority, for defence of a people, and Execution of juſtice on evil doers, may have their hand and work;
<note place="margin">Pſa. 83.15,16,17,18. Pro. 24.17.</note> yet they as Saints, are preſerved ſo, that they uſe valour and not violence, commit no rapes, ſeek not the ruine and deſtruction of men, but even in their overthrow and confuſion, deſire the fall and ſhame of them, may be bleſſed to them, as a means of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: whence alſo they rejoyce not in their ruine and harm, but as they are ſubdued, are very merciful to them; though when in their perverſneſs overthrown, they rejoyce in the righteous Judgement of God, and for their own deliverance;
<note place="margin">Prov. 16.4 1 Sam. 24.13.</note> their main deſign being the ſame with their Maſters, according to Goſpel-way, The Salvation of men: they know, that for revengeful, unnatural, and filthy actings in executing wrath, the Lord hath another Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men. Therefore the Saints being as men by humane Authority called, are Souldiers; and alſo as Saints, faithful; and ſo, though valiant and victorious in war, yet blood is not imputed to them, nor the Victory aſcribed to them, otherwiſe, then as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate called Inſtruments uſed together with others by Chriſt in his providential Government, and not as Saints and Partners with Chriſt:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.1,2,3,4.</note> This being his own, and in reſpect of Saints, as Saints, his alone work, by his Power in his Providence, to overthrow the Enemies. In which, his Garments are ſprinkled with the Blood of his Enemies; ſome of the Saints alſo dying in theſe Battels, his coming alſo approaching nigh. But being come, that Battel in which the Saints, and all the Saints, and none but Saints ſhall be with him, and himſelf perſonally and viſibly with them, and before them;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.5,6,7. &amp; 11.4. Mal. 4.1,2,3. Rev.
19.11-21, &amp; 20.1-4.</note> ſhall not be with carnal Weapons, nor Garments rolled in Blood, nor any confuſed noiſe, or any Saint dying; but the Breath of the Lord, and burning and fuel of fire, and all, and onely the wicked overthrown, as is ſaid. And this done, before he ſit on his Throne, and ſo raign, and the Saints raign with him; and then it will be: wait for it.</p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly, Conſider, That, as is ſaid, the Saints muſt not raign before their Maſter and Lord; and, that he receives his Kingdom from his Father, and then they receive it from him:
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.40. 1 Theſ. 4.14,15-18. 2 Theſ.
2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe muſt they not raign before one another; yea, not the ſurviving on Earth, before them that ſleep in the Lord: when we<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45953:16"/>are all gathered together unto him then, and not till then, ſhall this raigning be. If
<hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. muſt not have it before us; much more muſt not we look to receive it before them.</p>
            <p>And all theſe things conſidered, I ſuppoſe it will appear, That it is not from the Spirit of God, that any ſhould deſire and expect Chriſt to raign on Earth, as <hi>David,</hi> for the deſtruction of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, before he raign as <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſeeing all the Enemies of Chriſt, and his People at his coming, muſt be deſtroyed, before he ſo raign: nor as <hi>David</hi> was a type of Chriſt, is the Truth in Chriſt to be found by times and parcels; and if ſpiritually you would have
<hi>David</hi> a type of Chriſt's Shepherds Office, as he was King and Prophet, then for the firſt Fruits in this ſpiritualneſs, this raigning is not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them;
<note place="margin">Luk. 9.56. Act. 15.16,17. 1 King, 3.6.</note> and ſo by Goſpel-preaching, to build up the Tabernacle of <hi>David,</hi> the Courts of the Lord, in and for the Converſion of Souls. And as for
<hi>Solomon,</hi> he was given to <hi>David,</hi> as a Son to ſit on his Throne; and in that he was but a Type of Chriſt, the very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Son that is to ſit on the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> which will be <hi>when,</hi> and <hi>as</hi> is before ſhewn. And there is no ſtrength for this, in that conceit, That the Kingdom of Chriſt ſhould be for a time before his own perſonal appearance, in the Nature of a little Stone, to break in pieces,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor is it ſo ſaid either in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Expoſition, that in the Nature of a little Stone, it ſhall break, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that a Stone cut out of the Mountains with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hand, ſmote, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.34,35.</note> Now we know, That Chriſt is a precious Stone; and to ſome, a Stone of offence:
<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.16. 1 Pet. 2.6,7,8. Luk. 20.17,18. 1 Pet. 2.5. Heb. 8.2. 2 Cor. 6.4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>10. Phil. 2.4,5,6. Zach. 12.3. &amp;
14.5,9,12-15.</note> He is given of God, that framed his Body in the Womb of a Virgin, and raiſed him from the dead; and he in his firſt appearance was, and as diſcovered in the Goſpel, ſo ſtill is, diſallowed and deſpiſed of men, and beareth all with patience: and ſo little, yet the time is coming, when this Stone, how little ſoever now appearing, will break in pieces all wilful oppoſers; ſo likewiſe thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt are compared to Stones, and ſo even the Church on Earth (as
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) a Stone, and this not natural, nor of man's, but God's making; and becauſe deſpiſed and perſecuted by men, and they in patience bearing it, they alſo are in appearance to<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45953:17"/>men, and in their own eyes little; yet in the iſſue at laſt, they will prove a burthenſome Stone to all that trouble themſelves with them in perſecuting them. But ſurely, this will be at his perſonal coming, when the dayes of his patience come to an end: which if we believe, we may with patience wait for it.
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17,18. &amp; 4.1. Rom. 8.19,23. Col. 3.4. Phil. 3.20,21.</note> As for that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire and Expectation of ſome, by ſome Advancement here in the World that now is, to have a glorious manifeſtation of the Sons of God, before his perſonal coming, and reſtoring all things, it hath no Ground in Scripture, which expreſly affirmeth, That to be the very time. I forbear what of ſome Deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and Expectations might be ſaid: my Deſire is that we may deſire and expect nothing but what we have the Word and Promiſe of God for: and my Reaſon is, becauſe if ungrounded and unwarrantable Deſires and Expectations get rooting within us, they will lead to evil, and bring forth evil fruits, as a root of bitterneſs ſpringing up, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing many;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.15.</note> of which we are to beware: for,</p>
            <p n="1">Firſt,
<note place="margin">Jer. 17.6.</note> It will blinde us from ſeeing when good comes; ſo that, if God make of our Brethren Inſtruments of Deliverance, and ſet one of them in place of chief Governour; though he ſhould do his utmoſt by degrees, to get of the Saints for Under-Governors; though he afford us to worſhip God in Chriſt according to the Light we have received; yea, if he ſeeing us to differ, do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protect us from harm by others, but alſo from one harming an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; if he ſhould ſee a fleſhly deſire ſprung up in ſome Saints to be Rulers over all others in this World, he knowing all Saints are not yet agreed who are the Saints that ſhould rule, and ſuch Deſires unfit men for ruling; this being that would cauſe a worſe War than any yet hath been, and he in his Wiſdom and Love do ſtop it; If he ſuffer perſecution of Tongue and Pen, for theſe things, and do patiently bear it, and ſtill ſeek the Protection and Good of all, and Liberty for all Saints; yea, ſuch as ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite him: yet ſuch groundleſs and unwarrantable Deſires and Expectations, ſo blindes, that miſſing them, we ſee not the good in all this: but all we have, becomes to us like that <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had, of no eſteem:
<note place="margin">Eſth. 5.13. Col. 3.15. 1 Theſ. 5.18 1 Tim.
2.1.</note> ſo that neither God is acknowledged in his goodneſs, nor thanked by us; much leſs can his Inſtruments be, we ſo ſwerving from the plain Rule given us, I beſeech you, dear<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45953:17"/>Brethren, let us fly this great evil; which getting root, will bring forth more evil Fruits, ſhewing their contrariety to Grace in the very Face of them: for,</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly, where theſe unwarrantable Deſires and Expectations prevail, they lead,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1,2</note> To withdrawing our Prayers, and Endeavours to withdraw other from praying for thoſe in Authority, contrary to God's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 4.8. Pro. 25.9.</note> To diſcover what we conceive to be weakneſs in thoſe in Authority, contrary to Charity, and the expreſs Command; no Saint being without ſome weakneſs, though they have not the Temptations Governours have.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">Exod. 22.28. Eccleſ. 10.20.</note> To ſpeak evil of Rulers, to make them appear vile to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, contrary to the expreſs charge of God to us, concerning them.</p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 13.22.</note> By ſuch dealing, to ſad the hearts of the righteous, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the hearts, and ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked, that are ſet for ruine and deſtruction of all that are bent for, or profeſs godlineſs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Yea, under pretence of complaining of Perſecution, if croſt of our wills, to perſecute with Tongue and Pen, ſuch as with all their endeavour ſtrive to keep us from Perſecution; yea, when ſuch the care of the chief Governour, that I ſuppoſe no man can truely ſay. That by his authority and allowance, he is perſecuted for glorifying God, and advancing the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the Son of God, and the Son of Man; yea, for his ſufferings as Man, or Exaltation; or, as being the moſt High God or for bearing forth the Teſtimony of Chriſt in the Goſpel, or uſing any Ordinance of his commanded in the Goſpel; and ſo for his Conſcience in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God in and through Chriſt, however one Saint differ from another in the manner hereof, if they rebel not againſt the Government, to hinder the outward Peace of the Nation and Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>Oh my Brethren, I pray God keep us from theſe evils; and if any of us have run into them, and ſuffered ſome reproof for that, from ſaying, In ſuch things we ſuffer for conſcience ſake, or for good works, as Chriſt did: yea, rather let us minde and be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45953:18"/>for the mercies we enjoy, and live peaceably under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God hath ſo graciouſly given us: and in all, I pray ponder what the Scripture ſaith in all I have ſaid to you, my Brethren, whoſe reproach, for expecting the perſonal coming of Chriſt to raign with his Saints on Earth, I am very willing to bear my part in that with you, though I am perſwaded the term of Fifth-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy-men, was not by thoſe of underſtanding put on you for this Deſire and Expectation, but for deſiring and expecting a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for the Saints to rule over the men of the World, before his perſonal and viſible coming; which would be liker to Anarchy, than Monarchy. I ſuppoſe Charity will thus judge: and that it is according to Truth, in which Charity rejoyceth. I beſeech you therefore, as my Addreſs is more earneſt to you, ſo let me not be denied of you, to whom I have ſpoken in the laſt place. For, my Brethren, I would be loath any of thoſe hideous Brands, propheſied to be found in ſuch as walk in the way of <hi>Cain, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> and <hi>Corah</hi> in theſe laſt dayes, ſhould be found on any of us, as deſpiſing Dominion or Government, Preſumption, and ſelf-willedneſs, and ſpeaking evil of Dignities:
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10. Jude 8.</note> and I hope yea, am ſure, if we minde it, the grace of God will prevail with us to that which is better.</p>
            <p>And now to you all, Men, Biethren and Fathers Country-men and Neighbours, I pray let us ſearch the Scriptures; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their direction, let us be thankful for, and ſubject and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to, and live lovingly and peaceably under the Government God hath graciouſly put us under. I have not uſed any motives to you, from the faithfulneſs of him God hath made our Protector, as his ends from the firſt, if we could have attained that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly aimed at, even for advancing him that was before; his heart to all godly minded, and care for the Commonwealth, the ſignal Teſtimonies of God's approbation, and anſwer of Prayers in his manifold Tranſactions, his mercies to many in diſtreſs; yea, to ſome undeſerving, of which I might have ſaid ſomthing knowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: nor have I uſed any ſubtil or politick inſinuations: but my Ad to dreſs you, is onely in the Name of the Lord, with his Words, and in Bowels moved by the Teſtimony of Chriſt; the extent whereof,<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45953:18"/>as in Goſpel ſet forth, all that in heart believe, have a Priaciple with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their heart, leading to as much as I deſire; whoſe hearts, I fear it not, are with me in this Addreſs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I entreat all Men, and eſpecially Brethren, as we acknowledge the VViſdom, Love, and Goodneſs of God in his ordainment, in giving us this Government, and putting us under it: ſo let us accept it, ſubmit to it, pray earneſtly for bleſſing on our Protector, and all in Authority under him, and live under the Government with ſubmiſſion to the Higher Powers, obeying Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; and as far as is poſſible, live peaceably with all men, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace with all our Brethren: ſo ſhall we not hinder our ſelves of our deſired and expected good; but may ſtill expect the continuance and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe thereof to Governours and governed; and the God of peace will be with us. <hi>So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
